So let's start planning this component tree, shall we?
yleyse biz bu bileenleri planlamaya balayalm.
And for that of course, we need to define what our application actually is and what it should be able
Tabii bunun iin uygulamanzn gerekte ne olduunu ve ne yapmas gerektiini
to do.
tanmlamamz gerekir.
Keep in mind, we're building the burger builder application
Burger kurucu uygulamasn oluturduumuzu unutmayn.
so the goal is that users can use it to add ingredients and therefore build a burger.
Dolaysyla ama, kullanclarn malzemeyi katk maddeleri olarak kullanmalar ve bylelikle burger yapmalardr.
Now if we think about the UI and that is something you typically of course get by your designer or you
Artk kullanc arabirimi hakknda dnrsek ve tabii ki tabii ki tasarmcnz tarafndan alnyor
already create it
veya zaten oluturmusunuzdur.
but if we think about the UI, we probably have some header at the top navigation bar where we're then able
ve burada tm siparilerimize ve reticinin bulunduu yere gidebiliriz.
to go maybe to all our orders and where we have the builder itself,
Ancak bunu dnrsek, muhtemelen stteki gezinme ubuunda baz stbilgimize sahibiz
so the tool where we can build the burger and probably some logos, some text or an image to the left.
Yani burgeri ina edebileceimiz ara ve muhtemelen bazlar baz metinleri veya soldaki grntleri logolar.
Now the fine tuning, the colors sensor again, that is something you probably got by or designer,
imdi renklerin hassas ayarlanmas yine gnderiyor ki bu sizin veya tasarmcnz muhtemelen var.
we're not going to take care about this here,
Burada bununla ilgilenmeyeceiz.
we're going to add some colors as you create the application.
Siz uygulamay olutururken baz renkler ekleyeceiz.
Now what goes on the starting page? Let's say we're on the builder part here now,
imdi balang sayfasnda neler oluyor diyelim ki u anda retici taraftayz diyelim.
how should that look like?
Bu nasl grnmelidir.
Well of course it's only up to you but for me it makes sense that we have an area where the actual burger
size kaldm, ancak benim iin gerek burgerin ina edildii bir alana sahip olduumuz mantkl.
is getting built,
Elbette sadece
so where we see a preview of the burger we built. So that is super ugly here but that of course should be the
Dolaysyla burgerin bir nizlemesini grdmzde burada yaptmz bir orba var, ancak elbette bambaka
burger we're building with the different ingredients which get added dynamically as we add them. Now
olmal ki, u anda katk maddeleri ekleyebilmeleri iin dinamik olarak eklenen
to be able to add ingredients,
farkl malzemelerle ina ediyoruz.
we need some controls maybe sitting in a box or something like that below the burger. In there, we have
Belki bir kutuya oturan baz kontrollere ihtiyacmz var ya da bir burger
stuff like meat, salad, cheese maybe even bacon and so on and we essentially got a button to add or remove
yklemek iin byle bir ey var, et salatas peyniri belki pastrma gibi eyler var, vb. Ve biz aslnda her maddeyi eklemek ya
each ingredient so that we can well build our burger and then we probably also want to have a check out
da kaldrmak iin bir dme var, bylece biz de bizim burger ve sonra muhtemelen tm bir check-out
button,
dmesi istiyor.
so some button sitting below everything where we can tap on to buy our burger and obviously, we maybe
Bu nedenle, baz butonlar, her eyin altnda oturuyor ve burgerimizi almaya balyoruz ve akas biz bundan byle bir fiyata
also want to see a price or something like that below our burger as a preview so that we can always
bakmak isteyen bir burgerimizin altnda bir ey grmek isteyebiliriz, bylece maliyeti ne olduunu
see what it would cost.
her zaman grebiliriz.
Right now, this is the layout, the simple layout but which uses a lot of react concepts and which you
imdilik bu basit yerleimi ortaya koyuyor ancak ok sayda
can split up in a lot of components,
paraya blnemediiniz yeniden-aktarma kavramlarn kullanyor.
for example here, what we'll probably have is a root layout,
rnein burada muhtemelen sahip olacamz bir rota belirlenir.
so if we build our component tree we probably have our app component
Dolaysyla bileenimizi oluturursak, muhtemelen uygulama bileenimize sahibiz.
and in this app component, we might define a base layout for this application which basically would be
ve Melodia'nn sahip olduu veya syleyebileceimiz blm olacak DOS uygulamas iin bir temel tanmlayabiliriz.
the header and the part below the header, we could say.
Ve bu uygulama bileeninde, temelde balk
So if we add this here, we might have a layout component
Dolaysyla, bunu buraya eklersek, dzenlenebilir bir bileene sahip olabiliriz.
and we could also define that layout in the app component. The layout component probably as I just said
Ve hepimiz, muhtemelen, sadece dier bileenlerin i ie gemi olduunu syleyen, dzen bileenini
has a couple of other components nested besides it, some component responsive for navigation and for
uygulama bileeni ierisinde yerletirebileceini bulabildik. Buna ek olarak, gezinmeye ve navigasyonun ieriine kar duyarl
the content, so the navigation on the other hand might be split up in a tool bar and in a sideDrawer
olan baz bileenler de blnebilir bir ara ubuu ve bir site ekmece nk
because we want to create a responsive application
biz yantl bir uygulama oluturmak istiyoruz.
so we have to cater for both mobile devices and desktop devices.
Dolaysyla, hem mobil cihazlar hem de masast cihazlar karlamalyz.
So maybe below our layout, we actually have four different components.
Yani belki de Llyod'un altnda drt farkl bileene sahibiz.
We might have something like a toolbar which is always displayed and the items we display on it varies
Her zaman grntlenen ve zerinde grntlediimiz eler grnm penceresine gre deien bir ara ubuu
by the viewport,
gibi bir ey olabilir.
then we might have a sideDrawer, this is simply the side menu we can bring in when we're on the mobile
O zaman bir siteyle izme yapabiliriz mi yoksa yan ekmece iin mobil cihazdayken
device. For the sideDrawer
getirebileceimiz yan men midir?
we probably also want to have a backdrop,
Muhtemelen hepimiz bir zemin oluturmak istiyoruz.
so I'll add a backdrop here
Bu yzden bir zemin ekleyeceim.
too and having that backdrop here might make sense because maybe we also want to show a modal for the check
S Burada bu zeminin olmas mantkl olabilir, nk belki de kontrol etmek iin bir model gstermek
out
istiyoruz.
and then also want to have a backdrop on the root level of our dom basically.
Ve sonra da temelde yurt kk dzeyinde bir zemin istiyorum.
And then we want to have something which we can dynamically wrap, so whichever page you want to display.
Ardndan, dinamik olarak sarabilmemiz iin baka bir sayfaya gidebilmemiz iin ynlendirmeyi ekleyeceimiz uygulamada
Later in the app, we're going to add routing so that we can navigate to different pages
daha sonra grntlemek istediiniz sayfaya sahip olmak istiyoruz.
so we might want to display the burger builder page or the checkout page but all pages are going to
Dolaysyla burger oluturucu sayfasn veya deme sayfasn grntlemek isteyebiliriz ancak tm sayfalar
share that layout.
bu dzen paylaacak.
So we're essentially going to use props.children here,
Yani esasen ofis ov alann burada kullanacaz.
allowing us to dynamically pass a component in too depending on which page we want to do.
Yapmak istediimiz sayfaya bal olarak bir bileeni dinamik olarak geirmemize izin veriliyor.
So these are four components, props.children just as a dynamic component which we nest into our layout,
Bu yzden bunlar drt bileeni ocuu kendi dzenimize yerletirdiimiz dinamik bir bileen gibi soyuyoruz.
these are the four components we probably have on that layout area here.
Bunlar, muhtemelen bu yerletirme alanndaki drt bileenden oluuyor.
So let's quickly connect them to the layout then, shall we, like that.
yleyse hzl bir ekilde onlar yerleim blgesine balayalm ve sonra seveceiz.
Now our application is taking shape here,
imdi bavurumuz ekilleniyor.
what should we have below the toolbar then? In the toolbar,
Ara ubuunun altnda ne olmal, daha sonra ara ubuunda olmaldr.
we probably want to start writing the code already we need for the toolbar,
Muhtemelen zaten ara ubuumuz iin gerekli kodu yazmaya balamak istiyoruz.
so the hmtl code we could say, but the toolbar also might contain some components we add.
Demek istediimiz HDMI kodu ama ara ubuu da eklediimiz baz bileenler ierebilir.
For example we probably want to have a button which toggles that sideDrawer but we'll create these on
rnein, muhtemelen l kenar ekmecesini deitiren bir dme istiyoruz, ancak temelde bunlar yaratacaz
the fly basically and see how we split up
ve nasl blndmz greceksiniz.
but things to keep in mind here are basically the drawer toggle, so a button which targets the sideDrawer,
Ancak aklda tutulmas gereken eyler temelde ekmece geiidir. Dolaysyla, grntlemek istediiniz siteyi veya logoyu hedefleyen bir
logo which you want to display and our navigation items and I'm deliberately spanning navigation items below
dme ve gezinme elerimiz ve bu sitelerin altndaki gezinme elerini kastl olarak gsteren bir dme burada
these sideDrawer here too because there, we're also going to need navigation items
da vardr; nk biz de navigasyon elerine ihtiyacmz var.
and if we were to outsource navigation items into their own component, we might be able to actually share
Navigasyon elerini kendi bileenine dkaynakla yklersek, bunlar tp sava ve
them across the toolbar and the sideDrawer because we need the same navigation items, we just need to display
karar vericide paylaabiliriz, nk gezinme elerini sylemeliyiz, onlar farkl
them differently for different viewports.
bak alarna gre farkl gstermeliyiz.
So in the sideDrawer, we probably also want to use the logo then because again this is something you want
Bu yzden bir yan ekmecede, muhtemelen ayn zamanda logoyu kullanmak istiyoruz, nk yine bu,
to show in both viewports, just differently styled.
her iki grntleme panosunda da farkl tarzda gsterilmesini istediiniz bir ey.
So this might be how sideDrawer and toolbar are structured,
Dolaysyla bu, siber savan ve ara ubuunun nasl yaplandrld olabilir.
that backdrop basically will just hold some html code, we won't have nested children.
Temelde bu zemin yalnzca baz HVM'yi tutacak ve i ie gemi ocuklara sahip olmayacaz.
So that leaves us the props.children,
Bu bize Propst ocuklar brakyor.
that's of course important. Here
Tabii ki burada nemli.
we have different pages but for now we're only going to start with one page, that will be our burger
Farkl sayfalarmz var, ancak imdilik sadece bir sayfa ile balayacaz ya da
builder page, so a burger builder component.
BERTHER yapc sayfas yani bir burger oluturucu bileeni olacak.
Now how should that burger builder
imdi baban burger BUILDER nasl?
then look like? That burger builder in the end has to give us the build controls,
Sonunda o burger reticisi bize yerleik kontrolleri vermek zorunda deil gibi grnmeyin.
we have a look at our layout, the build controls, the part where we can add and remove meat, salad and
Etmene, et salatas ve peynir ekleme ve karma blmn ve kontrol
cheese and the check out button and the preview of the burger,
dmesini ve burgerin nizlemesini yerleik kontrollere bakyoruz.
these are the essential building blocks of the burger builder.
Bunlar, burger inaatsnn temel yap talardr.
So what we need in the end here is a couple of components, we need to have our build controls,
Sonuta burada ihtiyacmz olan ey, yap denetimlerimize ihtiya duyduumuz birka bileenden oluuyor.
again with all these ingredient buttons, we need to have the burger component giving us that preview of the
Yine tm bu Ingredion dmeleri ile burger bileeninin bize burgerin
burger and I also want to have some modal which gives us a
bir nizlemesini vermesine ve ayrca bize baz modallerin olmasn isterim.
check out preview, so where we basically see a summary and could proceed to check out, something like that.
Temelde bir zet grp grmediimiz incelemeyi kontrol edin ve byle bir eyi kontrol etmeye devam edin.
So these are the general components and again we might find a finer split or some subcomponents you
genel bileenlerdir ve yine yaratmak istediiniz bir finite plakas veya baz alt bileenler bulabilirsiniz.
want to create
Yani bunlar
once we actually start working on this
Bir kere bu konuda almaya baladk.
but for now, that's the split
Fakat imdilik blnmlk var.
I want to have here. Now if you think about the build controls then, how should these be structured, what's
Boulmu kontrolleri dndnz gibi imdi burada olmak istiyorum, sonra ne tlm kontrol
the build controls components content?
bileenlerinin ieriini yaplandrmanz gerektiini dnyorum.
Well it probably is a list of individual build control components,
Muhtemelen tek tek kay kontrol bileenleri listesidir.
so something like this, build control. It's of course one and the same component,
Dolaysyla bu yap denetimi gibi bir ey elbette bir ve ayn bileen.
just a list of it
Sadece bir liste.
so it might look like that and of course we probably also want to have our order button there, like this
Dolaysyla bor gibi grnebilir ve tabii ki muhtemelen de sipari butonumuzun byle olmas lazm, bylece bu burgeri
so that we have a button to check this burger out.
kontrol etmek iin bir dme var.
Now for that, we have to list for one but then we also have this order button additional sitting below
imdi biz varz, ama o zaman biz de bir altndaki ek oturma emri yok
it.
listelemek zorundayz.
Now the individual build control elements and the order button are probably just going to contain some
imdi bireysel kontrol elemanlar ve sipari dmesi muhtemelen sadece baz H M L
html, and with that I always mean jsx code.
ierecek ve bununla daima GSX kodu demektir.
Now how does the burger preview look like? The burger preview basically should hold a couple of ingredient
imdi burger nizlemesi burger nizlemesinin temel olarak birka bileen bileeni tamas gerektiini nasl
components,
gsterir?
so a list of ingredients which we dynamically manage of course, which the user dynamically manages with
Dolaysyla, dinamik olarak elbette ki kullanclarn dinamik olarak ynettii bileenlerin bir listesi,
the build controls.
kabadaylacak kontrollerle kartrlyor.
So that's the idea here,
te fikir budur.
we're going to have that list of ingredients below the burger component and each ingredient probably
Bombac bileeninin altndaki ieriklerin listesini alacaz ve her bileen muhtemelen
is just something like that div which either displays an image or where we create ingredient representation
grnt oluturan ya da Cs ile madde gsterimini yarattmz bir lm gibi bir ey.
with css, we will add this styling together of course. And the modal finally,
Tabii ki bu stilin yan sra hareketlilii de ekleyeceiz. .
well that probably should just be a wrapper component which in the end takes props.children to wrap
bir bileen oluturmas gerekir; bylece, teorik olarak, bir onay mesaj hatas grntleyen her ey iin kullanabileceimiz
itself around any content we want to render in a modal so that we have a reusable modal we could theoretically
yeniden kullanlabilir bir hareketlilie sahibiz mesaj veya sipari zetini vermeyi planlyoruz.
use for all kinds of stuff, displaying a confirmation message, an error message or an order summary as we plan
Sonuta, muhtemelen yalnzca pervane ocuklarn, kendisini bir modalde oluturmak istediimiz herhangi bir ieriin etrafna
to do. So
sarmas iin sarc
these are probably not all the components were going to add but it is a good overview over our tree.
Bunlar muhtemelen tm bileenleri alacak deil, ancak aacmz zerinde iyi bir genel bak.
We see that everything starts with one root component here at the top and then we split the tree up,
Grdmz gibi her eyin en stte bir kk bileeniyle balamas ve daha sonra kk bileeninin
having a layout which could be part of the root component
bir paras olabilecek bir dzene blnmesi.
as I mentioned and then having all the different branches. Now here, where we have the burger builder,
Bahsettiim gibi burada imdi burger yapmclna sahip olduumuz tm farkl dallara sahip olmak, bu
this will be kind of like a page.
tr bir sayfa gibi olacaktr.
It is a normal component
Bu normal bir bileen.
no worries, but we probably will add more pages throughout this course when we start adding a page where we
Endielenmenize gerek yok, ancak muhtemelen tm gemi siparileri ve bunun gibi eyleri grebileceimiz bir sayfa eklemeye
can see all past orders and stuff like that.
balarsak bu ders iin daha fazla sayfa ekleyeceiz.
Let's in the next step identify the state of our application.
Bir sonraki admda uygulamanzn durumunu belirleyelim.